{
  "reference_number": "223",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "A clear 2050 target will help to accelerate mitigation activities. The second half of the century is too unspecific and might be watered\n down to as far as 2100 by unambitious governments and industries."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "It is prudent to go for the most ambitious target because there will be plenty of resistance and inertia anyway. A less ambitious target\n\n might be watered down to a level where it doesn't achieve effective climate change mitigation."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "Depending on how NZ progresses, some international carbon units might have to be used to achieve targets and stay within\n\n budgets. I would like to see a cap for these, though, for example no more than 10% overseas reductions, or even a degressive cap\n that reaches 0% in 2050."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "30 years is a long time, and we need to be able to react to changes we are yet unaware of or can't yet predict. A revision to a more\n ambitious target should be possible at any time. A revision to a less ambitious target should only be possible under exceptional\n\n circumstances."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I would also be happy with a six-year period, or a period that is tied to the election cycle, to make sure that setting and reviewing\n\n budgets cannot become an election football at any time."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "This will provide enough flexibility to adjust future budgets without undermining short-to-medium-term budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Together with my response to #6 this will provide the necessary flexibility to be able to respond to unforeseen circumstances or\ndevelopments."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This is required to provide planning security for all parties involved."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The plans should be developed in close collaboration with the Climate Change Commission. The CCC should become the one-stop-\nshop for both government and business/industry as well as the public when developing and discussing plans."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "In case the government was giving in to political pressure or losing its track to meet the budgets and goals, the CCC could exercise\nsome influence by shaping the NZ ETS to counteract these issues."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "NZ hasn't progressed very far in terms of adaptation. I don't see mitigation and adaptation as isolated activities, because changes to\n\none could have an effect on the other and vice versa. It is prudent to bring them all under one umbrella."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It is particularly important that adaptation is coordinated at the national level, to avoid that regional or local authorities have to reinvent\nthe wheel and waste time and resources on adaptation strategies."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "M. bovis has shown us that voluntary reporting and monitoring doesn't work too well, unfortunately. Reporting needs to be mandatory\nto ensure quality results, which are needed to shape future policy and budgets. The money needed to set up mandatory reporting\n\nwill be well-spent."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Thanks for putting together a fantastic consultation document, and for providing us an easy and straightforward way to have our say."
    }
  ]
}
